<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Certaine observations touching the two great offices of the seneschalsey or high-stewardship, and high-constableship of England.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78478</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1713</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E122_23</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5060</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872781</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872781</idno>
            <idno type="VID">125227</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78478)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 125227)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 21:E122[23])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Certaine observations touching the two great offices of the seneschalsey or high-stewardship, and high-constableship of England.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for L. Chapman,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Octob. 17. 1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Lord High Steward --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  High Constables --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:125227:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CERTAINE OBSERVATIONS TOVCHING The two great Offices of the <hi>Seneſchalſey</hi> or <hi>High-Stewardſhip,</hi> and <hi>High-Conſtableſhip</hi> of ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>L. Chapman:</hi> Octob. 17. 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:125227:2"/>
            <head>CERTAINE OBSERVATIONS TOUCHING The two great Offices of the <hi>Seneſchalſey</hi> or <hi>High-Stewardſhip,</hi> and <hi>High-Conſtableſhip</hi> of ENGLAND.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Seneſchalſey or High-Stewardſhip of <hi>England</hi> is known to be the greateſt Office in <hi>England</hi> by reaſon of the authority it hath over all other Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> ſince the Norman Conqueſt hath long continued by deſcent inheritably in the Family of the ancient Earles of <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> was after tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated to the houſe of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> and by K. <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, of that ſtock, when he had obtained the Crown, was incorporate into the ſame, as all other the honours, Lands, and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditaments of that houſe were. For the plainer manifeſtation thereof, it will ſerve wel to the purpoſe, before the Office it ſelfe be deſcribed, to ſhew the firſt inſtitution thereof, and to recount in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſucceſſion of the Officers whilſt it paſſed inheritably.</p>
            <p>It is therefore to be underſtood that amongſt the perſons of chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt account which entred this Kingdome with D. <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:125227:2"/>and were aſſiſtant unto him in the conqueſt thereof, one <hi>Hugh Grauntmeſuell</hi> a Baron of <hi>Normandy</hi> was of ſpecial reckoning, whoſe father <hi>Robert</hi> of <hi>Grauntmeſuell,</hi> one of the chiefeſt Noblemen of all <hi>Normandy</hi> reteined at home with him for his own comfort, and for the preſervation of this ſtock, the elder of them named <hi>Robert,</hi> who ſucceeded him in all the inheritance of <hi>Normandy:</hi> but ſent with the Duke his ſecond ſon, called Sir <hi>Hugh of Grauntmeſuell,</hi> who ſo demeaned himſelfe in the enterpriſe, that when by conqueſt and ſtrong hand the whole Kingdome was ſubdued by the <hi>Normans,</hi> their Duke regarding the good ſervice of thoſe that adventured and laboured with him, forgot not the praiſeworthy deſetts of this No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleman, whom therefore he rewarded liberally with ſundry great Territories and portions of Land in many ſhires of the Realm; as namely with thoſe great Lordſhips <hi>Peberworth, Mereſtone, Quening<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, Weſton</hi> and <hi>Wileot</hi> in <hi>Gloceſterſhire,</hi> with divers Lands in <hi>Feren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, Meriſtow, Thorp, Welington, Staverton, Mereford, Newbottle, Middleton, Sutton, Biveld, Wodeford, Edgdow,</hi> and <hi>Ceroilton</hi> in <hi>North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amptonſhire,</hi> with <hi>Wichingſton</hi> and <hi>Hinkley</hi> in <hi>Leiceſterſhire,</hi> with divers Lands in <hi>Edwolton,</hi> and <hi>Sandy-acre</hi> in <hi>Nottinghamſhire,</hi> and with <hi>Ley</hi> in <hi>Suffolke,</hi> as appeareth by the record in the Exchequor commonly called Domeſday. Moreover he made him high Seneſchal or Steward of the whole Kingdom according to the <hi>Norman</hi> uſage, a dignity ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard of in this Land before, did further advance him in marriage with a great Lady inheretrix of ſundry poſſeſſions, named <hi>Adaliſa</hi> or <hi>Alice,</hi> on whom he gat two daughters, his heires, the elder of them called <hi>Petronelle</hi> or <hi>Pernell</hi> was married unto <hi>Robert</hi> Earle of <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>auecles blanches maines,</hi> that is, Robert with the white hands, that was the ſon of <hi>Robert le Roſſa</hi> Earle of <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> who was ſon unto <hi>Robert of Beanemount</hi> Lord of <hi>Pont Adomare</hi> and Earle of <hi>Mellent</hi> in <hi>Normandy,</hi> brother to Sir <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Newburgh</hi> the firſt Earle of <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke</hi> after the Conqueſt, unto whom the ſaid <hi>Pernell</hi> brought the one moyity of her fathers poſſeſſions, and withall for increaſe, becauſe ſhe was the eldeſt daughter, together with the honours of <hi>Hinckley,</hi> the Office of Seneſchalſie or Highſtewardſhip of <hi>England,</hi> which were not partable as the other inheritances were.</p>
            <p>The yonger of the ſaid Sir <hi>Hugh Grauntmeſſuels</hi> daughters called after her mother <hi>Adaliſa</hi> was given in marriage unto one <hi>Roger Bygot</hi> a Norman with the other moyity of her fathers poſſeſſions; unto
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:125227:3"/>whom ſhe bare divers ſons and daughters, from the eldeſt whereof named <hi>Hugh Bygot,</hi> that was the firſt Earle of the Eaſt-Angles of this family, containing <hi>Norfolk</hi> and <hi>Suffolk,</hi> the other <hi>Bygots</hi> that were after Earls of <hi>Norfolk</hi> are lineally diſcended: between which two families contention had often been about the Office of Stewardſhip, whereof in this place to note what is ſet down in the record of the Exchequer called the red booke is not impertinent to this purpoſe, where it is ſaid, that on the Sunday before <hi>Candlemas-day,</hi> in the 20, yeere of the raigne of K. <hi>Henry</hi> the ſon of K. <hi>Iohn,</hi> commonly called K. <hi>Henry</hi> the third, at the Coronation of his wife Q. <hi>Elenor</hi> that was the Earle of <hi>Provinces</hi> daughter, <hi>Simon of Mountford</hi> then Earle of <hi>Leiceſter</hi> and high Steward of <hi>England,</hi> lineally deſcended of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-named <hi>Parnell,</hi> being ready the day of the Coronation to execute his Office of Highſteward, which by right appertained unto him, was forbidden and gainſaid by <hi>Roger Bygot</hi> then Earle of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> who being deſcended from the before named <hi>Adaliſa,</hi> the yonger of Sir <hi>Hugh Grantmeſuels</hi> daughters, alleaged that it was his right to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe that Office, which controverſie (as alſo divers others then moved) was heard judicially before the King, unto whom Earl <hi>Simon</hi> replying anſwered, that it was true that contention had been heretofore mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved between their Anceſtors for the ſame matters, in the daies of King <hi>Iohn</hi> the Kings father, which was compounded and pacified for the ſervice of ten Knights, or rather ten Knights fees, given by the Earle of <hi>Leiceſter</hi> unto the Earle of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> who therefore releaſed all his title and right to the Highſtewardſhip.</p>
            <p>Whereunto becauſe Earle <hi>Roger</hi> of <hi>Norfolk</hi> alleaged that there reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of theſe Knights feet, two and a halfe to be aſſigned unto him, Earle <hi>Simon</hi> made anſwer that he might well recover them with the Arrera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges by the Laws of the Land, in the Kings Court, and ought not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to hinder him in the execution of his Office, ſeeing he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged the former accord; and by vertue of the ſame was already in quiet poſſeſſion of ſeven Knights fees and a half. And ſo was Earle <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> by the Kings own doom and ſentence admitted to the quiet exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of the Seneſchalſie at the ſame Coronation.</p>
            <p>And now to return where we left, <hi>Robert</hi> Earle of <hi>Leiceſter</hi> that wedded Dame <hi>Parnell,</hi> was high Seneſchall or Steward of <hi>England,</hi> and was the man for whoſe greatneſſe of ſtomacke the walls of the Town of <hi>Leiceſter</hi> were raſed to the ground becauſe he took part with
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:125227:3"/>the yong King <hi>Henry</hi> againſt his father K. <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, as hiſtories make mention, begat on her ſons and daughters, and after in K. <hi>Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> daies, the firſt, warring in the holy Land, was ſlain at the ſiege of <hi>Acon,</hi> in the yeere of our Lord God 1190, whoſe eldeſt ſonne <hi>Robert,</hi> ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mmed after his mother <hi>Fitz-Parnell,</hi> was after his death Earle of <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> and high Steward of <hi>England,</hi> of whom many worthy acts are by hiſtories remembred, both of his proweſſe in the field, and fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to K. <hi>Richard</hi> the firſt, with whom he continued as a moſt faithfull companion during the Paleſtine wars, was partaker of his evill fortune by being taken there priſoner, compelled to pay for his redemption 1000 Marks of Silver, and therefore conſtrained to ſell his Caſtell of <hi>Plaſey</hi> in <hi>Normandy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to be briefe and not to ſtay upon the Narration of theſe things. It ſerveth onely to the purpoſe, to note that he was one of our high Seneſchals, and dying without iſſue of his body, in the yeere of our Lord God 1204. was buried in the Abbey of <hi>Preux</hi> neere <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> leaving his two ſiſters to be his heires, between whom the whole in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance was divided, in the daies of K. <hi>Iohn. Amicitia</hi> the eldeſt ſiſter was married to <hi>Simon</hi> of <hi>Mountford</hi> yonger brother to <hi>Almarick</hi> Earle of <hi>Eureux</hi> in <hi>Normandy.</hi> And <hi>Margaret</hi> the yongeſt was wife unto <hi>Saher</hi> of <hi>Quencie,</hi> whom K. <hi>John</hi> made Earle of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> unto whom ſhe brought the one halfe of the Earldome of <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> and of the honour of <hi>Hinckley;</hi> and among other Lands, the Mannor of <hi>Grobye, Quitwicke, Shepeſhend, Hales, Brackly, South-Keſton, Timisbury,</hi> and <hi>Chimnomere. Simon of Mountford</hi> according to the Law and cuſtome of the Land, was in the right of his wife, being the elder ſiſter, made Earle of <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> and high Seneſchall of <hi>England,</hi> in the daies of K. <hi>Iohn,</hi> but he enjoyed not long thoſe honours, being for his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumacy and diſobedience, both he and his children ſhortly after ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed the Land, and his honours and poſſeſſions beſtowed on Earle <hi>Randolph</hi> of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> who held them a great time, except onely the Patronage of the Abbey of <hi>Preux</hi> neere <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> and the Office of the Stewardſhip of <hi>England,</hi> which the King kept in his own hands.</p>
            <p>This Earle <hi>Simor,</hi> a great warriour, was head and leader of the yong French King <hi>Lodowicks</hi> Forces, fighting againſt the Albigenſes about the City of <hi>Tholoſe</hi> where he was after ſhine. Theſe Albigenſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they began to ſmell the Popes treachery, and to controle the inordinate proceedings and diſcipline of the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Pope
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:125227:4"/>therefore accounting them as people hereticall, excited the French King to lay ſiege againſt the ſaid City of <hi>Tholoſo</hi> to expugne thoſe Albigenſes his enemies: But ſuch was the mighty protection of God fighting for his people againſt the might of man, that the French could doe no good with all their Engines and Artileries againſt the City but were forced to retire with great loſſe of people: among whom this Earle <hi>Simon of Mountfort</hi> generall of the Army, to whom the Pope had given a little before the Earle of <hi>Tholoſas</hi> Land, was ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with a ſtone before the gate of the City in the yeere of our Lord God 1219. as likewiſe was a brother of his beſieging of a Caſtle neere unto <hi>Thotoſa</hi> at the ſame time; he left two ſons of great fame, Earle <hi>Alt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arick</hi> of <hi>Mounfort,</hi> Conſtable of <hi>France,</hi> that was taken priſoner in the holy Land, and after his redemption in returning homeward dyed at <hi>Idruntum</hi> in <hi>Italy, Anno</hi> 1241. And <hi>Simon</hi> the yonger that after obtaining the good grace and favour of K. <hi>Henry</hi> the 3. whoſe ſiſter he married, was reſtored to the Earldome of <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> and to the integrity of his fathers loſt honours &amp; patrimonies in <hi>England:</hi> a man was he of great courage, and renown, well experienced in the wars, &amp; in matters of government, for long time had he been Seneſchall and Governor of the Countrey of <hi>Gaſcoigne,</hi> for the King of <hi>England</hi> his brother in Law, which of his own accord he reſigned contrary to the Kings mind, that greatly deſired to reteine him in good affection towards him, both becauſe he was a man of great power, wiſe and valiant, and for that the French laboured to make him their Seneſchall; but ſuch was the Earles hap that in the new begun variance between K. <hi>Henry</hi> and his Nobles for not obſerving the Laws of the Land, eſpecially ſuch new decrees as had been made at <hi>Oxford</hi> for the expelling of ſtrangers out of the Realm, he was choſen chiefe Captaine and leader of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, and for the time ſo much prevailed in the enterprize, that the King was by them taken in the battaile neere <hi>Lewes</hi> in <hi>Suſſex,</hi> together with his eldeſt ſon, and the King of <hi>Romans</hi> his brother, howbeit <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the Kings eldeſt ſon eſcaping out of their hands, renewed the war, and at <hi>Eveſham</hi> in battell ſlew this Earle <hi>Simon,</hi> and delivered his father from the hands of his enemies in <hi>Anno</hi> 1265 which was the 48 yeere of the raigne of K <hi>Hen.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that tooke part with Earle <hi>Simon</hi> were diſinherited, and their Lands given to ſuch as ſtood with the King; divers fled the real<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e, and amongſt them <hi>Simon</hi> and <hi>Guy,</hi> and the other ſonnes of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:125227:4"/>this Earle, which eſcaped into <hi>France,</hi> leaving no poſterity in this Land.</p>
            <p>The King afterward gave the Earledome of <hi>Leiceſter</hi> to his yonger ſon <hi>Edmond</hi> that was the firſt Earle of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> and to his heires, which ever afterward cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nued in the houſe of <hi>Lancaſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r,</hi> who beare the title of <hi>Leiceſters</hi> Earledome, and withall held and enjoyed the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the high Stewardſhip of <hi>England,</hi> untill the ſame, with all other the honours, Lands and hereditaments thereunto belonging, was uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Crowne in the daies of King <hi>Henry</hi> the 4. being of that ſtock, till that now of late it pleaſed the moſt Noble and vertuous Pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ceſſe Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eene <hi>Eliſabeth</hi> our gratious Soveraigne to revive the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and title of <hi>Leiceſters</hi> Earledome in the perſon of the right noble Lord <hi>Robert</hi> of <hi>Dudley</hi> younger brother and heire to the right noble Lord <hi>Ambroſe</hi> Earle of <hi>Warwick</hi> and Viſcount <hi>Liſle,</hi> both ſonnes to the high and mightie Prince <hi>John</hi> late Duke of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> line<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally deſcended and heire in bloud of the bodies of <hi>Robert</hi> of <hi>Beaumount</hi> Earle of <hi>Mellent</hi> aunceſtour to the before-mentioned Earles of <hi>Leice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> and of <hi>Hen.</hi> of <hi>Newborough</hi> Earle of <hi>Warwick</hi> Anceſtour to the Earles ſonne, both brethren as before hath been declared, and living in the time of the <hi>Norman</hi> conqueſt, as more plainly is ſhewed by Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>degrees deduced.</p>
            <p>Thus much declared by way of preface or ingreſſion to the matter in hand, and to ſhew that the office of High Stewardſhip of <hi>England</hi> hath heretofore paſſed inheritably in diverſe families, as other great Offices have done.</p>
            <p>It remaineth now to declare what theſe Stewardſhips are, with the authorities and prerogations to them belonging, and to produce ſuch notes and obſervations as are extant touching the ſame.</p>
            <p>And to begin with the chiefeſt,
<note place="margin">Seneſchall.</note> the Seneſchalſey or Stewardſhip of <hi>England,</hi> as it is not to be doubted of, but that it took beginning from the Normans, and was by them, firſt eſtabliſhed in this land after their great conqueſt, and victory over the Engliſh Saxons in the yeare of our Lord God 1066 by their example of their home government in <hi>Normandy,</hi> where the Duke had under him for his chiefeſt Officer a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſchall or Steward, ſo cannot the right of this office be better or in briefer ſort deſcribed then by ſetting downe of the Dukes Steward faithfully in ſuch ſort, as it is to be ſeene written in the old cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomary booke of the Duchie of <hi>Normandy</hi> in theſe words following.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:125227:5"/>
            <p>In times paſt there was to wander throughout <hi>Normandy</hi> a certaine Juſticie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> greater then theſe before mentioned, who was called the Princes Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſchall or Steward he was wont to perfect and amend that which the other Juſticiers had left undone, he kept the Prince, his land, the lawes and rights of <hi>Normandy</hi> he cauſed to be obſerved and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, all that was not right done by the Bailiffes, whom he removed from the Prince his ſervice, if he ſaw it expedient ſo to doe.</p>
            <p>He was once to viſit the Prince his forreſts and incloſures, to keepe Courts of the forreſts, to enquire how they were uſed, their cuſtomes he commanded to be obſerved delivering right to everie one as the ſame by antiquity grew due, or by Charter had been confirmed unto them, ſo diſcreetly conſerving the Prince his rights that in the obſervation of them he notwithſtanding hurt none of his ſubjects. Such as upon diligent enquirie he found faultie and to forfeit, within the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, either in trees, or in wilde beaſts, or in free fowle, he was wont to puniſh by the purſe, or for want of ability that way by long impriſonment. He chiefly gave his minde to keep the countrey in peace, and ſo wandrlng hither and thither throughout <hi>Normandy</hi> once everie three yeares did viſit all the parts and Bailiages thereof. To him it belonged to make enquiry in every Bailiage of the exceſſe and wrongs done by the under Juſticiers, and likewiſe of common robbers, of violent deflowrers of Virgins, of murthers, of burnings, and of all thoſe things which belong to the pleas of the ſword, whereof peace and reformation had not been had in courts. Of all other cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minall facts he likewiſe diligently ſearched and upon enquiry cauſed juſtice to be done throughout, he cauſed enquiry to be made of treaſure digged under ground, of wrekes caſt upon ſand, and other the Prince his rights, the removing of waters, and the ſtopping and hindering of their courſes did he reduce unto their old forme, ſo as their paſſage might be hurtfull to no body, if any man were minded to turn the courſe of any water running thorow his own grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, the banks, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of on either ſide were ſiituated within his own fee he might lawfully do it, ſo as the ſaid water when it paſſed out of his ground might be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed into his old channel without any mans hurt or hinderance. It is to be underſtood notwithſtanding that none may ſtop the courſe of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ordinary running ſtreames within his banks or ditches longer then from the riſing to the going down of the ſunne. Neither may any one ſtay the courſe of waters with any new ponds diches or ſluces, but ſhall permi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to run their courſe, leſt the mills ſtanding upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their ſtreams
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:125227:5"/>And Or men in their affairs, Tanners, Diers, and ſuch like ſhould thereby ſuffer loſſe and detriment. If any ſhall ſtay them for the filling up of his pools or ponds, they ſhall be bound to reſtore ſuch loſſes as the Milners or others living by the paſſage of thoſe waters ſhall have ſuſtained by the with-holding of them, and waters ſhall be ſuffered to run their accuſtomed courſe. No man may erect a Fiſhing, or build a Mill, unleſſe the water-banks on either ſide be within his own Fee, wherein he hath Liberties, Weares, or other ſuch like things: for fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings may not be made in running ſtreams, becauſe by them oftentimes the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are corrupted, yet notwithſtanding they may bring the waters by Ditches and Trenches out of the running River into their grounds, ſo as the ſame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn not back into the running ſtream.</p>
            <p>It belongeth alſo unto the Steward to cauſe the bounds and limits of Towns and Villages the ſtreets and paths to be revoked to their antient ſtate and to ſee that old accuſtomed highways be opened; for no man may in theſe caſes alledge for excuſe any lett or hinderance, wherefore he ought not to make amends un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Prince. As for towne ditches and common ſtreets, which ſerve to no private perſons poſſeſſions, but are common unto all. If they be by any uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped or incroached upon, they ought to be reſtored to the common benefit, and they that doe occupie them, ought not to eſcape puniſhment.</p>
            <p>All theſe things appertaine unto the Office and charge of the Seneſchall, for the due execution whereof there needeth not neither plea nor aſſiſe, but where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he found cauſe, and he did therein, and provided as he ſaw needfull and expedient.</p>
            <p>This farre-forth is the High Stewards office deſcribed in the old cuſtomarie booke of the Dutchie of <hi>Normandy,</hi> from whence came the firſt inſtitution of the ſame with us in this Kingdome, eſtabliſhed no doubt with no leſſe authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and priviledge here under the Kings of this Land, then the ſame was then practiſed under the Dukes of that Duchy, whereof there is an eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall title written, though nothing Clerke-like among other matter in an old booke of Parchmine belonging as it is ſaid unto the learned Lawyer and skilful Antiquarie Maſter <hi>William Fleetwood</hi> Eſquire, one of the Serjeants at the Law, and Recorder of the Citie of <hi>London,</hi> which word for word followeth.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Here is ſhewed who is to be High Steward of</hi> England, <hi>and what his Office is;</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Seneſchallie or high Stewardſhip of <hi>England</hi> belongeth to the Earle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> and of old time did thereunto appertaine; And it is to be underſtood, that it is his Office under and immediatly after the <hi>King</hi> to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſee
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:125227:6"/>and governe the whole Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> and all the Offices of the Juſtice within the ſame Kingdome in all times both of Peace and Warre in manner following.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The manner how and when the Lord High Steward ought to exerciſe his Office by duty and Oath of Fealty is ſuch.</head>
                  <p>VVHenſoever any man or woman ſhall come into the Kings Court in whatſoever Court it be and poſſibly unto the K. himſelfe to ſeeke for redreſſe againſt injurie done unto them, and he or ſhe be not able in due ſeaſon to obtaine remedie. Then the High Steward of <hi>England</hi> ought and is bound to receive their Petitions and complaints, and to keepe them untill the next Parliament then after to be holden and to aſſigne unto ſuch Complainants if he thinke good, a day wherein they may exhibite and proſecute their Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and in full Parliament in the preſence of the King to reprehend and blame that Officer or thoſe Officers, who ever they be, that ſo have failed in doing of Juſtice, and thoſe thereof call to accompt unto whom in ſuch caſes every one throughout the Kingdome is bound to anſwer, the King onely excepted.</p>
                  <p>If the Chancellour of <hi>England</hi> have failed of making originall remedy, and amends, and the Juſtices. Treaſurers, Barons, &amp; Chamberlain of the Exchequer, Steward of the Kings houſe, Eſcheators, Coroners, Sheriffs Clerks, Bayliffs &amp; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther officers of what places and reſpects ſoever they be in their Proceſſes Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Executions of Judgements, and Juſtice to be made to the favour of th'<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one &amp; loſſe of th'other party, for gifts bribes or other procurements ſhal fail or give over at the leaſt-wiſe if any Juſticier, when as both parties pleading before them ſhall ſtand in Judgement, ſhall by ſuch falſe procurements deferre judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, contrary to Juſtice, and the Lawes and cuſtomes of the Land: If then the Chancellour of <hi>England,</hi> or any other of the Kings officers in ſuch caſe ſhall alledge in Parliament and ſay for their excuſe, that in that caſe ſuch hardneſſe and doubtfulneſſe of the Law and rights did ariſe, when the ſame was heard and propounded before them that neither he nor the Court of Chancerie or any other Court wherein he is an Officer, were able or knew to attaine unto the ſafe determination of the right; Then ſhall he open and declare the ſame Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biguitie and doubt in Parliament; then if it bee found that the Law was doubtfull in that Caſe, the Chancellour or other Officer ſhall be held excuſed, and then ſhall the high Steward of <hi>England,</hi> together with the Conſtable of <hi>England</hi> in the preſence of the King and other of the Parliament make choice of twentie five perſons more or leſſe, according as the caſe ſhall require, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with ſuch other caſes in that Parliament rehearſed, amongſt whom ſhall
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:125227:6"/>be Earles, Barons, Knights of the Shire, Citizens and Burgeſſes, who there ſhall ordaine, agree upon and eſtabliſh remedy by Law in all ſuch Caſes, for ever after to endure; And thoſe Lawes ſhall be recited written and allowed in full Parliament, and ſealed with the great Seale, and delivered forth to all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Law and Juſtice from thence forward to be holden for Lawes and in publick places, where it ſhall be thought expedient, they ſhall be proclaimed and divulged, whereas all other common Lawes, and chiefly Statute Lawes throughout all the whole Kingdome, ought to be publickly proclaimed.</p>
                  <p>If ſo it happen that there was in ſuch like caſe either Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon Law or Statute-Law, ſo that the Kings Steward, and others of the Parliament may underſtand and perceive, that ſuch default and delayes in Proceſſes and Judgement doe happen by ſuch Officers, when as the deceipt and malice of ſuch Officer hath openly and often before beene apparant, then ſhall he be removed out of his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and ſome other fit officer ſhall be put in his place; If they ſhall preſume a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Juſtices and ſuch other Officers, as by excuſing themſelves ſhall ſay, that they have not heretofore known themſelves and the Courts, whereby they are in ſuch Caſes to deliberate and take adviſement; Then ſhall they be admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed by the Steward, on the behalfe of the King and the Parliament, to ſtudie and ſearch better the Common Law, that no ſuch ignorance or negligence bee found in them in the like Caſes afterward.</p>
                  <p>If they ſhall happen to offend in the like againe; they then to be put out of their offices and other diſcreeter and more diligent perſons ſhall by the King and his Counſell be aſſigned to their roomes.</p>
                  <p>Likewiſe it is the Stewards office, if the King have evill Counſellours about him, that adviſe him to doe things, tending openly and publickly to his diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, or to the diſ-inheritance or publicke hurt and deſtruction of his people.</p>
                  <p>Then the Steward of <hi>England,</hi> taking with him the Conſtable and other great eſtates, and other of the Commonaltie ſhall ſend to ſuch a Counſellour, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding him in ſuch ſort to lead and counſell the King, and of ſuch his evill Counſell ſhall make rehearſall, enjoyning him to depart from the Kings pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and longer not to abide with him to his diſhonour; and the publick hurt, as is aforeſaid, which if he ſhall not doe they ſhall ſend unto the King to remove him from him, and to give no more eare unto his Counſell, for that amongſt the people he is eſteemed to bee an evill Counſellour to the King againſt his Subjects.</p>
                  <p>If hereupon the King doe not put him away, againe and often ſhall they ſend aſwell unto the King as unto him.</p>
                  <p>If at the laſt neither the King nor ſuch Counſellour of his have regard unto the Meſſages and requeſts made unto them, but ſhall refuſe to doe thereafter;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:125227:7"/>Then for the Weale Publick it is lawfull for the Steward, Conſtable of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> noble men and other of the Commonaltie of the Realme with Banner in the Kings name diſplayed to apprehend ſuch Counſellour, as common enemie to the King and the Realme, to commit his body to Ward untill the next par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and in the meane time to ſeize upon all his goods, lands and poſſeſſions, till Judgement be pronounced of him, by the adviſe of the whole Kingdome in Parliament, as it happened unto <hi>Godwine</hi> Earle of <hi>Kent</hi> in the dayes of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Confeſſour, next predeceſſour to <hi>VVilliam</hi> Duke of <hi>Normandie,</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour of <hi>England,</hi> who for ſuch ill Acts and Counſels of his, was deprived of his Earldome, Eſcheted to the aforeſaid King, notwithſtanding at the Kings and Noblemens permiſſion, <hi>Godwine</hi> came againe into <hi>England,</hi> and did after forfeit as before.</p>
                  <p>And as it happened likewiſe to <hi>Hubert</hi> of <hi>Burgh,</hi> Earle of <hi>Kent,</hi> in the time of King <hi>Henry,</hi> that was Sonne of King <hi>Iohn,</hi> who for his evill deeds and bad Counſell was apprehended, and by the high Seneſchall, and other Peeres de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of his Earldome, by the allowance and conſent of the whole Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</p>
                  <p>And likewiſe did it befall unto <hi>Pierce</hi> of <hi>Gaveſtone,</hi> who in the dayes of King <hi>Edward,</hi> the Sonne of King <hi>Henry</hi> for ſuch his evill Acts and Councells was baniſhed out of all the King of <hi>Englands</hi> Dominions, as well on this ſide, as beyond the Seas, which <hi>Pierce</hi> of <hi>Gaveſton</hi> afterwards by the Kings means, and by the favour and permiſſion of the Nobilitie returned into <hi>England,</hi> and had of the Kings gift the Earldome of <hi>Cornwall,</hi> yet was he after that for his evill deeds and Counſels baniſhed the Realme againe by the Nobles and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and his aforeſaid Earldome Eſcheated to the King, but returned after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards without the Noblemens leave and conſent, and did reſort and aſſociate himſelfe unto the King as before he had done, which when the High Steward, Conſtable, and others of the Nobilitie underſtood, he was by them apprehended, and beheaded at <hi>Blacklow</hi> in <hi>VVarwick</hi>-ſhire, as a publicke enemy to the King and to the Realme.</p>
                  <p>So have you as much as in the ſaid old Booke is to be ſeene touching the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the High Steward of <hi>England,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>After the death of any King or Queen abſolute of this Land the high Steward of <hi>England,</hi> by vertue of his Office ſitteth judicially, and keepeth his Court in the <hi>Whitehall</hi> of the Kings Palace at <hi>VVeſtminſter,</hi> neere unto the Kings Chappell, and there receiveth the Bills and Petitions of all ſuch of the Nobilitie and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as by reaſon of their tenure as, or otherwiſe claime to doe ſervices at the new Kings Coronation, and to receive the Fees and allowances therefore due and accuſtomed. As did <hi>Iohn</hi> Duke of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> Earle of <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> high Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:125227:7"/>of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. at the Coronation of King <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, and <hi>Tho. Pierce</hi> Earle of <hi>Worcester,</hi> who exerciſed the ſame Office of the Coronation of King <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth as ſubſtitute and Deputie to <hi>Thomas</hi> the Sonne of the ſaid King <hi>Henry</hi> then being very young, unto whom his Father had aſſigned that Office, being parcell of his owne inheritance, who before hee had obtained the Crowne, was not only Duke of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> as his Father <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Gaunt</hi> had, but alſo was Earle of <hi>Darbey, Lincolne, Leiceſter, Hereford,</hi> and <hi>Northampton,</hi> and by the Earledome of <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> inheritably alſo Lord high Steward of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And ſince the time that the ſaid Office hath beene extinct in the Crowne by the Deſcent of the ſame unto King <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, as heire to Dame <hi>Blanch</hi> his Mother, Daughter and Heire to <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> Earle of <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> and high Staward of <hi>England:</hi> experience ſheweth that upon the Arraignment and Tryall of any Peer of the Realm; that is to ſay, Duke, Marqueſſe, Earle, Viſcount, or Baron, or any of their Wives or Widdows upon Indictment of Treaſon or Felony, the ſheweth to grant the Office of the high Stewardſhip of <hi>England (pro illa vice tantum)</hi> to ſome Peer of the Realme by Letters Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, the tenour whereof hereafter enſueth, who inſtead of the Lord high Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, that by ancient Law hath been holden for a competent and indifferent Judge betweene the King and ſuch Peers, ought and always hath uſed to be Judge, and give ſentence of Acquicall or Condemnation upon the Peere ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigned.</p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="patent">
                              <head>The tenor of the Patent.</head>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>Regina &amp;c. Praeclariſſimo Conſanguineo &amp; Conſiliario ſuo</hi> A.B. <hi>&amp;c. ſaltem ſciatis quod cum</hi> G. D. <hi>Marchio</hi> E. <hi>indictat. existit, &amp;c. ac pro eo quod oſſicium Seneſchall. Angliae cujus praeſentia pro adminiſtratione juſtitiae &amp; executionis ejuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem in hac parte facienda requirit, ut accepimus jam vacat: de ſtrenuitate, fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, provida circumspectione &amp; induſtria veſtris plurimum confidentes, ordinavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, &amp; conſtituimus vos ex hac cauſa Seneſchallum Angliae, ad officium illud cum omnibus eidem officio in hac pante debitis ſive pertinend. hac vice gerendis, occupan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis, &amp; exercendis. Dantes &amp; concedentes vobis tenore praeſentium plenam poteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem indictam entum praedictum cum omnibus idem tangendis a praefat. juſtitia noſtris recipiendis &amp; inspiciend, ac ad certos diem &amp; locum quos ad hoc pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viderit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>sipſum Marchionem, e&amp;c. coram vobis evocandum &amp; ipſum ſuperinde au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diendum, examinandum &amp; respondere compellendum ac ſine debito terminandum, Nec non tot &amp; tales Dominos Proceres, &amp; Magnetes hujus regni nostri Angliae; ejuſdem Marchionem, &amp;c. &amp; alios pares per quos rei veritas in hac parte melius ſcire poterit, ad diem &amp; locum praedictum ex cauſa praedict. coram vobis comparere aſtringerdum, &amp;c.</hi>
                              </p>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:125227:8"/>
                  <p>Thereupon the Lord High Steward directeth forth a precept to the Juſtices before whom the Indictment is taken, willing them to certifie the ſame Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at a day and place by him aſſigned.</p>
                  <p>And doth likewiſe direct another precept to one of the Serjeants at Arms, for the Summonition of the Peeres againſt the day of tryall in theſe words.</p>
                  <p>A.B. <hi>comes, &amp;c.</hi> I. N. <hi>ſervienti Do nini Regis ad Arma ſalutemetibi praecipio quod ſummon. tot &amp; tales Dominos, Proceres, &amp; Magnetes, hujus regnt Angliae praedict.</hi> C. D. <hi>Marchionis:</hi> E. <hi>&amp;c. &amp; aliorum pares, per quos rei veritas melius ſcire poterit, quod ipſi perſonaliter compareant coram me apud Woſtmon.</hi> 1 <hi>die</hi> Junii, <hi>&amp;c. ad faciend. ea quae ex parte Domini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Regis, tunc thidem in praemiſſis injungent, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The like precept doth he alſo ſend to the Lievenant of the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> for bringing forth the Peere, being priſoner to his tryall and judgment.</p>
                  <p>It appeareth that at the Common Law, before the twentieth yeere of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, a Subjects having title to lands, which are in the Kings poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, might have a Writt to the Sheriff of the County, where the Land doth lie againſt the King after this manner.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Praecipe</hi> H. <hi>Regi Angliae quod reddat</hi> S. L. <hi>centum acras ter. in</hi> D. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But whether the Writt ſhould be a Ward under the Teſte of the High Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard or Conſtable of <hi>England,</hi> that is to be doubted of.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Touching the Office of the Lord Steward of the Queens Houſe.</head>
               <p>OF the Lord Steward his Office of the Queens Houſe, being thorowly well known to the chiefe Officers of the Houſhold, It ſeemeth needleſſe to ſet down any notes, or obſervations, at all by reaſon of the daily and continuall execution thereof ſtil in practice, howbeit becauſe there is left unto us from elder age, a forme thereof, is greatly to be regarded in theſe our days, this place ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth fitly for the exemplification of the ſame, ſo in ſuch ſort as it is ſet down in an old Book of Record, called <hi>Domus Regis Angliae,</hi> preſerved in the Counting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe of the Houſhold, wherein the whole State of the Kings Houſe is orderly deſcribed. And this Office amongſt the reſt after this manner enſuing.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Steward of the Kings Houſhold.</head>
                  <p>THe Steward of the Kings Houſhold receiveth his charge of the Kings high and proper perſon, and the Houſhold ſtaffe in thoſe words following. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſchall <hi>venetz le Baston de noſtre Maiſon,</hi> By which forthwith he is alſo Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard of the Marſhalſey, that is the Court of Houſhold, of which he is a Judge of Life and Limbe; and except thoſe caſes, the Treaſurer, Comptroller, Coffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:125227:8"/>two Clerks of the Green-cloth, and the chiefe Clerk of Controllment, for any matters elſe done within the Houſhold, or appertaining thereto, they fit with him at the Board of Doome, that is at the Green-cloth in the Compting houſe, as Recorders and Witneſſes of the Truth.</p>
                  <p>The ſtate of all this excellent Houſhold is wholly committed to be ruled and guided by his diſcretion, and all his commandements in Court to be obeyed and obſerved.</p>
                  <p>Alſo within the Houſhold except the Kings Chamber, alway to be obſerved, covered out of the Kings preſence, what great eſtate elſe that be preſent, as for a cup, a cupboard, and diſhes, but none aſſay.</p>
                  <p>Alſo while he is preſent in Court, there ought no new commandement, charges of Officers, or any other perſon be made without commandement firſt of his perſon, for the Offices more ſure diſcharge.</p>
                  <p>Alſo in the Houſhold rules and judgments hee repreſenteth the Kings eſtate, his ſtaffe is taken as for a Commiſſion,</p>
                  <p>Alſo he may in houſhold of his power, adnull any cuſtome not medled with worſhip and profit; or change it, and erect a new, ſuch as ſhall ſeem to his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom by adviſe taken at Compting board, for the better, and to the King and his Houſhold of more honour and profit.</p>
                  <p>And in that he is head Officer, he giveth example to all others to be of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernance with inordinate rule to be contented with moderate Coſtages within the Court in Liveries and Services taking Dinners and Suppers in the Hall and in his Chamber, or in any other Office as often as it pleaſeth him to ſearch and ſee the good ſaid rules, and the directions in them.</p>
                  <p>He hath daily in the Hall eating one Chaplain two Eſquires foure Yeomen, and in his Chamber daily for his breakfaſts, and his Chamberlains meat at Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and Livery for all night, eight Loaves, foure Meſſes of great Meat, two re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards of Roaſt, two Pitchers of Wine, ſix Gallons of Ale from Hollandtide till Eaſter, one Torch to attend upon himſelf, one Tortays to fetch his Livery by three Perches of Wax, ſix Candles of Wax, eight Candles <hi>per</hi> 5. viij Tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, foure Faggots, Litter and Ruſhes all the yeer, of the Serjeant Uſher of the Hall and Chamber, and after Winter ſeaſon, foure Shyddes, two Faggots, and when him liketh to have more largely in any thing then his Chamberlain that doth fetch it, or receive it, muſt record thereof by Taile or Bill into the Comp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting houſe.</p>
                  <p>Alſo the Steward taketh of the Compting houſe for his Fee at Eaſter and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaelmaſſe, twenty Marks, and for his Robes for Winter and Summer at the Feaſts of Chriſtmas and Whitſontide ſixteen Marks, and for his Napery at the foure Feaſts of the yeere by even portions, three pieces of Linnen Cloth in
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:125227:9"/>the great Spicery, or in money therefore of the Compting houſe, in all 13 l. 1 s. 4 d.</p>
                  <p>And he hath one Yeoman of his Chamber ſtill abiding, whilſt himſelf is out of Court to keep his Staffe, taking for his Livery daily one caſt of bread, two meſſes of great Meat for noon and night, one Gallon of Ale.</p>
                  <p>The Steward and Treaſurer of this honourable Houſhold, repreſent within it the State of an Earle.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Item,</hi> The Steward or Treaſurer, or one of them is bound to be at the Comp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting houſe, at the awayt of the daily Accompts of Houſhold; and by the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Noble King <hi>Edward</hi> the Thirds Statutes. In caſe it paſſe for lack of them three days unaccompted, that then they two ſhall acquite the Coſtages of the Kings Houſhold for one day of their own proper coſts.</p>
                  <p>The Steward and Treaſurer make a Warrant yeerly at Michaelmas to the chiefe Butler of <hi>England,</hi> aſſigning him for how much Wine, and in what pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Kings Houſe, he ſhall lodge the ſame for the yeer following. For the daily expence of his Houſhold, which hath and muſt with good overſight be ſure of three hundred Tuns, And for other things look the Statute of noble <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, Anno</hi> 15. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 21.</p>
                  <p>Thus much out of the Book called <hi>Domus Regis Angliae.</hi> Sir <hi>William Stam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> the Judge in his Book of the Pleas of the Crowne under the title of <hi>qui Iudgera treaſon, &amp;c.</hi> who ſhall judge of Treaſon and Felony, by reaſon of their Offices without Commiſſion, and who not, mentioneth the Statute made, <hi>Anno</hi> 33.44. 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 12. Whereby it is ordained that the great Maſter or Lord Steward of the Kings Houſe only, and in his abſence, The Treaſurer and Controller of the Houſhold with the Steward of the Marſhalſey, or two of them, whereof the Steward of the Marſhalſey to be one, may without Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion heare and determine of Treaſons, of miſpriſion of Treaſons, of Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Manſlaughters, and Bloudſheds perpetrated within the Kings Houſe; for theſe, ſaith hee, are great and chief perſonages in whom the King repoſeth ſuch truſt, that hee hath ordained them eſpecially, for the ſafety and good Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Realm and Houſhold.</p>
                  <p>More hereof is to be read in the Volumes of the Statutes, 25 of <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 21, 3 <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 14.33. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 12. Wherein the preheminences of the Lord Steward of the Kings Houſhold are rehearſed, needleſſe therefore in this place to be recited.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
